# **IQBAL HUSSAIN**

22, Markham Road, Ashok Nagar, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India - 560025

lincoln@live.in | www.iqbalhussain.in

#### **Profile**

I am a full stack developer and a big fan of free and open source software. My experience primarily lies with the use of Python, Django (a Python based web framework), Android application development and managing various AWS services such as EC2, S3, RDS etc. My interest is being involved in every phase of the software development process. I have 2+ years of Python/Django experience. I am also comfortable building user interfaces for Internet browsers using plain JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX, CSS etc.

# **Areas of Expertise**

- Programming Languages: Python, JavaScript, Java
- Databases: Redis, PostgreSQL, MySQL, Oracle RDBMS, Realm
- Platforms: GNU/Linux, Windows, Android
- Backend Technologies: Django, RESTful web services using DRF, Celery, Gunicorn, Nginx,
   Memcached
- Frontend Technologies: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX, Android, JSON
- Tools: Git, SSH, Bash, PyCharm, Android Studio, Eclipse, vi, MySQL Workbench, SQL Developer, Adobe Photoshop, Microsoft Office
- laaS/PaaS: AWS EC2, Heroku, Google App Engine, PythonAnywhere

#### Online Profiles

- Linkedin: http://in.linkedin.com/in/igbalhusn
- **Github:** https://github.com/igbalhusen
- Stackoverflow: http://stackoverflow.com/users/3775598/iqbal

# **Employment History**

**Full Stack Developer** 

May 2016 to Present

Edelweiss Broking Limited - Bengaluru, Karnataka, India

#### Backend

- Started developing with *Django 1.9*
- Building RESTful APIs using *Django-rest-framework (DRF)*.
- Using *Celery* to manage asynchronous task queue.
- Using *Redis* as the message broker in Celery.
- Using *Pdfcrowd* API to convert webpage to PDF file.
- Using easy-thumbnails to make thumbnails from images
- Using **SendGrid** to send emails.
- Tweaked DRF templates to block public access to API documentation.
- Using *celery beat* to schedule various asynchronized tasks.

#### **Android**

- Integrated Google Sign-In and Facebook Login for Android.
- Using *Retrofit* to call APIs.
- Using *Picasso* to load images.
- Using *Realm* to store data on device.
- Using *android-crop* to crop images.
- Integrated *Fabric Crashlytics* to log all app crashes.
- Integrated *Firebase Analytics* to log various events on app.
- Used *AppIntro*.

#### **Associate Product Developer**

March 2015 to April 2016

WealthPack - Gurgaon, Haryana, India

- Building RESTful APIs for the consumption by mobile as well as web apps.
- Integrating user authentication system.
- Facilitating token based authentication.
- Using Yahoo Finance API to convert currency rates.
- Sending **GCM push notifications** to Android app.
- Sending email notifications using *Mandrill* templates.
- Implementing real-time push notifications using PubNub
- Using Celery to handle asynchronous tasks.
- Writing custom Django management command to populate freshly created database taking data from CSV files.
- Using *Django-cors-headers* to fix cross origin issues.

- Using memcached to cache API responses.
- Using Selenium to automate browsers and Beautiful Soup for screen scraping.

#### **Backend Developer**

November 2014 to March 2015

Empower Futures - Ahmedabad, Gujarat, India

- Started developing with Django 1.7
- Building RESTful APIs using Django-rest-framework (DRF).
- Handling user registration, activation etc.
- Facilitating token based authentication.
- Using Google Map API.
- Using Celery to manage asynchronous task queue.
- Using Redis as the message broker in Celery.
- Using Facebook Graph Search API.
- Using Python Social Auth to authenticate users through their Facebook, Google Plus accounts.
- Link multiple social accounts to a native user.
- Writing test cases and perform unit testing.
- Creating hooks for the git repositories.
- Writing scripts for collecting data from spreadsheets and loading them into database.
- Writing script for various data manipulation operation in database.
- Creating *sitemap* to inform search engines about URLs that are available for crawling.
- Creating *robots.txt* to advise cooperating web crawlers and other web robots about accessing all or part of a website.
- Handling user authorization at both model-level and object-level using *Django-guardian*.
- Using *Amazon CloudFront* to deliver static contents.
- Using Firebase to handle real-time notifications.
- Using *Git* for all projects.

#### Freelance Web Developer

July 2014 to November 2014

- Developed web sites using *Django*, *HTML*, *CSS*, *Javascript*, *jQuery*.
- Deployed sites on PaaS (Platform as a service) like *Heroku*, *Google App Engine and PythonAnywhere*.

- Technical support to clients on phone, and over the Internet.
- Managed client relationships, and finances.
- Fixed various cross-browser formatting issues of web pages.
- Worked for a long time in a machine learning project called SkyRELR (www.skyrelr.com).
- Made a download feature in the SkyRELR project which allows users select multiple
  files and when they press the download button, the selected files get compressed at
  the back-end and the compressed file is served to the users. The compressed file is
  not saved in the auxiliary memory of server.
- Used *Django-registration* for two-step user registration process.
- Used *Django-paypal* to allow users purchase product online with their PayPal account.
- Used *django-tastypie* to build a REST API that allows access data in JSON format.
- Used D3.js to build a dashboard using data retrieved by the REST API generated by Django-tastypie. The dashboard was made interactive with filter feature powered by AJAX and jQuery.
- Git version control tool has been used in all projects.

# **Education**

#### Master of Technology, Computer Science and Engineering

2014

CVR College of Engineering - Hyderabad, Telangana, India

 Completed Post graduation in Computer Science and Engineering with 79.2 percentage of marks.

### Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science and Engineering

2012

Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University - Hyderabad, Telangana, India

• Graduated in Computer Science and Engineering with 64.6 percentage of marks.

#### Higher Secondary, Science

2007

B.N. College - Dhubri, Assam, India

- Intermediate education (12<sup>th</sup> grade) in science stream with Physics, Chemistry,
   Mathematics and English as main subjects.
- Passed with 71.6 percentage of marks.

#### **High School Leaving Certificate**

2005

Agomani Higher Secondary School - Agomani, Dhubri, Assam, India

• Secondary education (10<sup>th</sup> grade) completed with 73.2 percentage of marks